if you followed along in all the tutorials on
this channel you are beginning to have a good
understanding of how the GrandMA3 software
works and you are on your way of being a GrandMA3
programmer now i think it's time to look at
some different GrandMA3 programming techniques
in this episode i'll show you how you can program
GrandMA3 sequences and how you can manipulate
the cues to do quite amazing things i'll show you
a lot of different techniques that can help you
when you start making your own GrandMA3 shows
so be sure to watch the video all the way to the
end so you don't miss any shortcuts or something
you didn't know you you needed or something you
didn't know the grandma3 could do so let's get
into it let's start by making two simple cues
let's first of all take all our vipers and
we turn them on we put them in a position
like this we give them a color then we take all
ours we do the same thing turn them on give them
a position and give them a color like this and
then we take all our dimmers just turn them on
so this is basically cue number one so let's store
this into a sequence an empty sequence here let's
label the sequence to our master master cue
list maybe a master sequence we could call it
like this as you can see it over here it's
empty but as soon as i click it you can see
what's going on let's relabel the first cue to
start cue like this and then we need to assign
it to a fader up here so we say assign we take the
sequence and we assign it to fader number 201 as
you remember maybe if you have seen followed
along the tutorial series you can manipulate
the faders up here and what we need to do is go
into the section up here and just add this section
because i need a go minus button as well right
now we have a go plus down here so we can go
forward in our cue list we need to be able to
go backwards as well so let's close this down
let's clear the programmer and let's go into cue
number one like this now we need to to be able to
see the changes we need to make cue number two so
let's take all our vipers make them all white and
make them go into the downstate center position
then we can take all our dimmers and we can turn
them off and we can store this into cue number two
so create second cue let's call this ds-center
there we go so if we clear the programmer
again and we go from we cue number one we
go to cue number two everything happens but it
happens really really fast and we don't want that
so we go into the fade option here and we set
it to let's say five seconds there we go and
then we go back to cue number one again and when
we go into cue number two it's gonna nicely fade
from one cue to the next in five seconds so
that's really cool and as you can see here all
the dimmers turned off and everything moved and
the vipers change color to white over five seconds
but maybe we want everything turning off to
do that faster and there's a really really
easy way to do that you can simply right click
this one and you can say fade in is five seconds
and you can use the dash here and say fade out
is one second and if you say please here and
you go back again this is cue number one all our
dimmers up here should turn off now in one second
and everything else should fade in five seconds
so we say go and as you can see they turned off
a lot faster than the rest of the movement here
so that's a really really easy way to do fade
in and fade out times you find yourself using
that a lot if you are doing theater maybe or
even rock concert as well this is a really easy
way to do it you can do it individually as well
and right now we are in cue number two you could
basically say edit enter that's always going to
open up the cue you are in on the selected cue
list if you have a lot of cue lists some a lot
of sequences it's going to select whatever is
selected up here so that's another way of doing
it you can do it individually you can say all
dimmers you can go into the fade option here and
you can set a different time in here and update
your queue it's going to do exactly the same
thing and it's going to help you if you need to to
have many different out times in one single queue
but let's clear this and maybe exit out of
the editor and say okay this is cue number two
let's turn off all our vipers because we need to
set them up with a gobo so let's turn them off and
store that in cue number three here and we can
say viper off and let's turn them back on again
and maybe put in a gobo and then let's store that
in cue number four there we go and we can say gobo
on let's work with wait times right now all
the vipers are turning off if we clear the
programmer and we go into this one it's going to
happen instantly we don't want that so let's set
a fade time of two seconds and we go back and
now they're going to fade out in two seconds
very nice but now when i go into the next cue
they're going to turn on again in zero seconds and
all the gobos are probably gonna go through the  the fixture you can see that if we go back you
can see that again you see all the gobos moving
we don't want to see the gobos moving so we need
to give it some sort of wait time so we need so so
if the dimmer waits maybe half a second to come up
the fixture needs the time to to set up the
gobos behind the scenes so if we say gobo on
here and we say edit enter or edit please we
go into our vipers we go into our dimmer here
and we go into the delay option and we can
simply set a delay of maybe half a second
like this and we need to update our cue
list there we go clear the programmer
we go back one queue so in our previous cue we
had all the vipers on into the downstage center
position the next cue turned all the vipers off
and now we need to turn them all on again but
without seeing the gobo action and we did that
by delaying the dimmer only about half a second
so when i press go it's going to come up nice
and easy instead of coming up really really fast
and maybe we need to set a fade in time as well
let's say we said a two second fade time as well
now we are in cue number three and we need
to go to cue number three and you can see
it's sorry cue number four and you can see it
turns on really nicely let's just do it again
right now they are off we go and they
cue up the gobo and then it turns on
so we just simply delay it a little bit and that
is also very very helpful you'll find yourself
doing that when you are dealing with gobos and you
are actually doing it as well when you're dealing
with media servers because sometimes a media
server needs a few milliseconds to cue up the
the clip you have on the on the server so this is
going to help you a lot to do some split timings
as you can see working with GrandMA3 cues is
simple but there's a lot more in this episode so
make sure you stick around for the last part and
if you enjoy this video and find it useful be sure
to give it a like. liking videos is a great
and free way to support any youtube channel
and it sends a signal to youtube to show the video
to more people and please leave a comment below
if you have anything on your mind i mean it's
always nice to hear from you getting some kind
of response makes it a lot more fun to make these
videos and if you're interested in GrandMA3
hardware i have some links in the description
for all kinds of different pieces of GrandMA3
hardware a small disclaimer though is the links in
the description are all affiliate links that means
if you decide to purchase some of the products
i will receive a small commission on the sale
but let's continue so let's see what else we can
do let's build a sequence right next to the other
one where we take all the color out of the vipers
we take all the vipers we take the color out or
we just choose the open white color we store
this into a separate sequence let's label it
white there we go and we select it and we can
see this sequence over here so if we clear the
programmer and we maybe assign this sequence on
a fader up here we go into the options here and
we add the next row of buttons here and we make
the top button and off button then i can go this
sequence and i can turn it off again that's
fine everything turns on in white that's cool
but let's maybe go into the cue here maybe we
should just label it white as well there we go
so we clear this one let's say we need to
split the time of this cue so let's go into
our cue here let's say edit please that loads
everything into the programmer let's take all our
vipers and go into the color and sorry we need to
go into the color when we need a delay time here
we set it to zero through one second
please and now we need to update this cue
and it's been updated and let's clear
out so right now if we turn it off
on the off button up here and i go the cue you
can see it comes in as a split time between zero
and one second and that is really
cool so let's make a new cue here
where we take all our vipers again and put it
back to the magenta color and we store this
in a second cue and we do exactly the same
thing we can go back to magenta right here
and we do the same thing we go into
the cue like this we say edit please
and we do the same thing on the delay we set
it from zero through one second and we update
the cue like this and we clear the programmer
once again so in when i go into cue number one
it's gonna do all the white in and when i go into
cue number two it's gonna take it out again and
here comes the fun part we can actually we can
actually make it go directly to the next cue
so instead of this down here being a go button we
can right click and set a time for it or we can
make it a follow cue let's just make it a follow
cue so you can see what happens i go into cue
number one they turn on and it follows right
next into cue number two so let's see it again
and it takes it all the way out so the follow
cue follows as soon as the previous cue
is complete so if i change this into a timed
cue for instance i can set a trigger time
of maybe 0.6 seconds then it's going to follow
actually before this one is done and it actually
makes some kind of cool effect so if i off it
again and i go into the cue when you see what's
happening it's going to take it out again so you
now made some kind of actually really cool effect
without using the phaser engine at all let's
just see it again it goes into white and it
it takes it back to magenta so that's a really
really cool effect doing doing this with split
times is actually very very very cool so if you
are in your master cue list and you needed to
trigger the cue list next to it you can actually
use the command line or use a command line
command in in the cue list so let's just uh
clear everything out here and let's just store an
empty cue into this one this is cue number five
and there's nothing in it and let's go down to the
command section down here we have cue number
five and we select it and we say go sequence
sequence two
if i go into my master cue list now and i press go
i'm in cue number two we go into cue number three
let's just go into cue number four
and as you can see here i have a cue
with nothing in it but it's
gonna go sequence number two
which is this one and see what
happens when i press go on this one
you saw that that's really really
cool so you can use this bump effect
you can simply push it or you can assign it to
another another cue or sequence or whatever
and you can remote trigger it from there GrandMA3 programming is cool and remember that we are
still in the very early stages of the software as
i explained in the last tutorial as well i'm sure
that GrandMA3 software will evolve a lot over
the next few years just like the early days of the
GrandMA32 software be sure to give this video a
like so you can spread it out to more people and
subscribe to the channel if you don't want to miss
any future episodes or you can start the GrandMA3
tutorial playlist and you can start from episode
1 and i promise that you will know what it's all
about when you have seen all the episodes so far
i try to release one video per week so please come
back if you want to continue learning GrandMA3  programming and if you are on the journey of
learning GrandMA3 programming as a beginner
i highly suggest that you watch this next video
in this video i will show you some other
cool features of the GrandMA3 software
i hope to see you on the channel again in
the future and until then happy programming